I'm Raising a Son Alone After a Divorce
I am living with my son after divorce.
Maybe my special attention to my son for
living without a father had a negative effect
He is very timid and
doesn't have close friends.
He often blames me and
we often get into fights.
He is 20 years old.
He took an SAT recently.
He didn't do well
due to a lack of focus.
He wants to repeat one more year
to get into the field of study
he wants and I support that.
But I'm worried if he won't
be able to focus next year as well.
Though I hate him
when he causes me pain,
I feel bad about not providing
the right environment for him.
It's best to enter a university this year.
Suggest it to him.
If he still wants to repeat one more year,
you can let him,
but, you can't get involved.
Whether he studies or not, plays,
whatever he does, don't get involved.
Because you didn't have a husband and
had no one to share your love with,
you doted on him too much. As a result,
he doesn't have a vision for his future.
This will hurt your feelings, but,
he doesn't have much chance to succeed.
Too much expectation and attention
has become a heavy burden to your son.
Therefore,
you need to distance yourself from him.
The problem is not lack of affection.
It's too much attention.
Stop paying attention to your son and
start paying attention to yourself.
Why are you living alone in this day
and age? Aren't you even dating?
You don't want to remarry?
Your son will be much better off
if you remarry or have a relationship.
Put your attention to somewhere else.
You need to find something to put your
energy into and stay away from your son.
With no relationship,
no one to give your heart to,
and no religion,
all your attention is focused on your son.
That's why he is not doing well.
We fought a lot during
his SAT preparation period.
And after the test, he said to me,
"Mom, if I have to repeat,
I would like to study at a prep school
with a dorm that's far away from you."
That sounds like a good idea.
If you can afford it, send him far away.
Don't ever go see him for the whole year.
If he comes home, you leave the house.
(Audience Laughter)
(Questioner) My son tells me
the same thing.
(Questioner) He said he won't come home
until after he is done with the SAT.
Too much attention is not good for him.
Also, he will have trouble getting married
When his girlfriend comes over,
she will notice
that there is another woman
attached behind him.
That's not a good thing.
If you don't want to ruin him,
take your hands off him now.
Pay attention to another man
instead of your son.
(Audience laughter)
Unless you want to marry your son,
let go of him. You are ruining his life.
The best thing to do is to come to the
temple, practice and do volunteer work.
You are paying attention to him,
not because he is your son,
but because he is a man.
So, I am telling you to pay attention
to another man.
Why would a celibate monk advise a woman
to pay attention to another man?
Because you are leading your son
on a ruinous path.
Go have an affair, go date, get remarried.
Have other interests and
live your own life.
Stay away from your son.
He is crying out loud but
you are not aware of it.
Don't worry about providing
a good environment,
cooking delicious food,
or buying nice clothes for him.
Don't worry whether he eats or not.
Since he graduated high school,
he will be 20 this year, right?
Twenty-one.
He's now an adult, so let go of him.
Whether he gets a girlfriend,
or whatever he does,
unless he gets into violence,
theft, sexual assault,
lying, or swearing,
don't get involved.
(Questioner) Thank you.
(Applause)
After your husband passes away,
instead of remarrying, you stay alone
enduring all kinds of hardship
and making sacrifices.
But, that does ruin your child.
Without a husband,
too much attention goes to the kids
which impedes their development.
How can urine be used?
It can be a fertilizer, right?
However, if you give urine to a bud,
will it help or kill the bud?
It will kill it.
You give urine to big trees.
If you urinate under a big tree,
you fertilize the tree.
But, if you do it to young grass,
you will kill it.
The way is not anything special.
Which direction you urinate
that is tao, the way.
(Audience Laughter)
So, you give attention where it's needed.
Giving attention where
it's not needed makes matters worse.
You should take care of a young child
no matter what sacrifices you have to make
During adolescence, you just watch him
go through trials and errors,
and making mistakes.
You shouldn't get involved.
Upon adulthood, you should
let go of the emotional ties.
Respect your child as
an independent person.
You should not nag.
You sacrifice yourself thinking
you are doing the right thing.
And you end up ruining your child.
Isn't that foolish?
Seek your own happiness.
Don't believe you sacrificed
your life for your kid.
Who has to pay you back
for your sacrifices, then?
Your child. How can a child bear
such a heavy burden?
So, never think you sacrifice
your life for your kid.
It's your responsibility
to take care of a small child.
Once he is older,
allow him to live his own life.
Treat him with respect
You also live your own independent life
This way, it's good for everyone.
(Applause)